(
"ai_sub_version": "3.6.0",
"generated_at": "2026-10-04T01:58:46.151084",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"service_tier": null,
"service_tier_subtitles": null,
"service_tier_lyrics": null,
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
おーー
Ooooh!
お主ら聞こえる？
Can you guys hear me?
お主らーー！
Everyone!
あれ？
Huh?
YouTube調子、復活した？
Is YouTube back up and running?
聞こえる？
Can you hear me?
大丈夫そう？
Is it looking okay?
聞こえる！
You can hear me!
挨拶するのじゃ！
Time to do the greeting!
あらあら、めらめら、あちち、めら！
Ara ara, mera mera, achichi, mera!
ほらほら！遊び回り隊、火の用心担当の緋崎さらまんだ、あちち、めらなのじゃ！
Hora hora! I'm Hikishio Saramanda, in charge of fire prevention for Asobimawaritai, achichi, mera!
のじゃ。
Noja.
聞こえた？オッケー？
Did you hear me? Okay?
大丈夫そう？
Is everything okay?
ちょっと心配なのじゃ。
I was a bit worried.
なんかYouTubeが...
Because YouTube...
に、今「要改善」って...
...currently says "Needs Improvement"...
YouTubeに、今のわしの配信の調子みたいな評価が...
YouTube's rating of my current stream status...
YouTubeからの今の電波とかの評価が「要改善」...
...the rating of my connection from YouTube is "Needs Improvement"...
「要改善」になってるのじゃ。
...it says "Needs Improvement."
どう？大丈夫かの？
How is it? Is it okay?
どうかの？
How is it looking?
聞こえる？大丈夫？
Can you hear me? Is it okay?
大丈夫ならいいの。
If it's okay, then that's good.
今日お主何した？
What did you do today?
お仕事じゃった？
Did you have work?
「入り直したら行けた」？
"Rejoining fixed it"?
入り直して、入り直してほしいのじゃ！
Please try rejoining! Rejoin, everyone!
お主ら入り直して！
Rejoin, everyone!
いけるかの？
Will it work?
お仕事、学校？今日休み？
Work, school? Or was today a day off?
「おみくじ引いた」？あ、そう！
"You drew a fortune"? Oh, really!
ショート動画、ショート動画で、おみくじ、出したのじゃ！
I posted a fortune-telling Short video!
「秋葉でグッズ買った」？やったのじゃ！
"Bought merch in Akiba"? Awesome!
秋葉なんか、外のモニターみたいなやつにも、遊び回り隊が出ているとの噂。
Rumor has it Asobimawaritai is on the outdoor monitors in Akiba!
明日試合？部活とかかの？いいの、青春じゃの！
A match tomorrow? For club activities? Nice, youth is great!
「大吉じゃった」「小吉」
"I got Great Blessing", "Small Blessing".
テスト？テスト期間なの？今、テスト期間なの？
Exams? Is it exam week? Is it exam week right now?
「一発大吉」！すごいのじゃ！
"Great Blessing on the first try"! That's amazing!
「わしを見るため帰ってきた」？わしのために？
"I came home to watch you"? For me?
やったのじゃ！嬉しいのじゃ！
Yay! I'm so happy!
「要努力」？
"Needs Effort"?
「要努力」も入れてみたのじゃ。
I also included "Needs Effort".
あの「要努力」って言葉がめっちゃ好きで。
I really like the phrase "Needs Effort."
あの、わし『磯部磯兵衛物語』っていう漫画があっての。
You see, there's a manga I like called "Isobe Isobee Monogatari."
そう、『磯部磯兵衛物語』って漫画が好きなのじゃが。
Yeah, I love the manga "Isobe Isobee Monogatari."
そこに出てくる、あの「要努力」っていうのが、
And the "Needs Effort" that appears in it...
超好きで、超好きで。あ、YouTube直った！「非常に良い」になってる！
...I love it so much. Oh, YouTube is fixed! It says "Excellent"!
さっきまで、なんか改善、要改善みたいになってたが、非常に良いになってる！やったのじゃ！
It said "Needs Improvement" earlier, but now it's "Excellent"! Yay!
うん。
Yeah.
『磯部磯兵衛』知ってる？あの、「処すよ、処すよ」みたいな、聞いたことない？「処すよ」みたいな。
Do you know "Isobe Isobee"? Have you heard them say "I'll execute you, I'll execute you" or something?
あれ『磯部磯兵衛物語』に出てくる、あの、将軍？将軍だっけ？
That's from "Isobe Isobee Monogatari." Was it the Shogun? The Shogun, right?
なんか「お兄ちゃん、こいつ処す」みたいな。
Like, "Brother, execute this guy."
なんか、むずむずする。花粉？
My nose is tickly. Pollen?
お、大きかった音、大丈夫じゃった？ごめんなのじゃ。
Oh, was that sound too loud? I'm sorry.
ちょっと、きゅう、急に出て、急に出てびっくりしたのじゃ。
It just came out suddenly, it surprised me.
ちょっと鼻水噛むからミュートさせてほしいのじゃ。
I need to blow my nose, so let me mute for a second.
今日ね
Today, you see...
今日ね、あの、わしがね
Today, you see... I...
あの、ち、ご飯ちゃんと食べてるかな、とか
My father was wondering if I was eating properly,
お部屋ちゃんと片付けられてるかなって、あの、父がね
and keeping my room clean...
人間の父がね、わしのことを拾ってくれた人間の父がね
My human father, the one who took me in, you see...
あの、お家来てくれてね、お部屋片付けて
He came over to my place, cleaned my room,
母が作ったご飯持ってきてくれたのじゃ
and brought me food made by my mother.
なんか、デビュー前とかもね、デビュー前とかも
Even before my debut, actually...
あの、やっぱ親というものは、子の健康が心配みたいでの
It seems parents always worry about their child's health.
あの、ご飯をね、母が作ってね、届けてくれるのじゃ
My mother would make food and have it delivered.
うん、おにぎりとか、唐揚げとか作っての
Yes. Things like rice balls and fried chicken...
ケーキとか作っての
She even made cakes,
なんか冷凍しての、わしがの、食べるんじゃ
and froze them for me to eat.
うん
Yes.
優しいのじゃ
They are so kind.
うん、そう。それでね、あの、デビュー準備期間から今まで
Yes. And you see, from the preparation period until now,
なんかすごい、あの、今まで自分が思ったことないくらいパタパタしてての
I've been busier than I ever imagined.
それで、お部屋にダンボールの山ができてての
Because of that, a mountain of cardboard boxes piled up in my room.
デビュー、超前じゃったらダンボールとか捨ててったんじゃが
If it were way before the debut, I would have thrown them out,
今ちょっと、Amazonとかのダンボールでいっぱいになってての
but right now, it's filled with Amazon cardboard boxes.
それを父がの、あの、一個ずつ折りたたんでの
And my father folded them one by one...
片付けてくれたのじゃ。うん。
and cleaned them up for me. Yes.
父と母はすごくわしのことを応援してくれてるのじゃ
My father and mother really support me.
うん
Yes.
家族愛じゃの
It's family love.
人間の家族愛じゃのって思ったのじゃ
I felt that it is human family love.
うん
Yes.
うん？
Hmm?
父と母は人間なのじゃ
My father and mother are human.
わしが、あの、渓谷で痛い目を見て、山から下りて
I got hurt in a valley, came down from the mountain,
拾ってくれたのが父と母なのじゃ
and they took me in.
人間の親
My human parents.
サラマンダーじゃないのじゃ
They are not salamanders.
わしはサラマンダーじゃが
I am a salamander, though.
なんか、犬を拾う感覚と近いと思って頂ければ
You can think of it as similar to taking in a dog.
わしは拾われたサラマンダーなのじゃ
I'm a salamander that was rescued.
きょうだい？一人っ子なのじゃ
Siblings? I'm an only child.
うん、なのじゃ
Yes, that's right.
優しい人間がわしのこと拾ってくれましたのじゃ
A kind human took me in.
そう、種族違うけど、父と母、優しくしてくれてすごいのじゃ
Yes, although we are different species, they treat me so kindly.
本当のご両親？わしのことを産んだサラマンダーの親は知らないのじゃ
My real parents? I don't know the salamanders who gave birth to me.
会ったことないのじゃ
I've never met them.
認識もしてないのじゃ
They don't even recognize me.
わしってどうやって生まれたんじゃろう？
I wonder how I was born.
お父さんとお母さん配信見てる？え、配信は
Are my father and mother watching this stream? Well...
なんか見てるっぽい...
It seems they are watching...
なんか見てるっぽいのじゃ！
It seems they are actually watching!
あ、なんか、あの、すごい
Ah, that's really...
でも、父も母もSNSやってないから
But since neither of them use social media,
なんか、全然あんまりわかんないのじゃ
they don't really know much.
アカウントとか持ってないんじゃが
They don't have accounts,
それでもなんかこう、検索？
but they seem to... search?
検索とかで見つけて見てくれてるっぽいのじゃ。うん。
They seem to find it by searching and are watching. Yes.
見られてるのじゃ
They are watching.
全部見てるかは知らんけど
I don't know if they watch everything,
なんか、すごかった、なんか、動画？
but they said my debut stream video...
初配信の動画、すごかったって褒めてくれたのじゃ。うん。
was amazing, and praised me for it. Yes.
のじゃ
Yep.
そう
Indeed.
そして、今日は
And today...
「空気読み。」というゲームで
I'm going to play a game...
遊ばせていただこうと思いますのじゃ！
called "Kuukiyomi"!
なんか、わし
Since I'm...
サラマンダーじゃから
a salamander...
人間のコミュニケーションにあまり自信がなくて
I don't have much confidence in human communication,
人間社会への溶け込みにあまり自信がなくて
and I'm not very confident in fitting into human society.
デビュー前とかも、そのホロライブの先輩とか
So even before my debut, to get along well...
ReGLOSSのメンバーとかと仲良くなるために
with my Hololive seniors and the members of ReGLOSS...
道徳の教科書とかいっぱい読んで勉強したんじゃが
I read many moral education textbooks to study.
それでもまだ、人間社会のこと分かりきってない
But even so, I feel like I still don't fully understand...
気がする
human society.
分かりきってない気がするけど、でも
I feel like I don't fully understand it, but still...
うん
Yeah.
「こころのノート」は読んでないのじゃ、うん。道徳
I haven't read "Kokoro no Note" (Heart Notebook). Yes, moral...
道徳の教科書読んだのじゃ
I read moral education textbooks.
何冊か読んで、なるほど、と、人間について知ったのじゃ
I read a few books and learned about humans.
だから
And so...
今日は
Today,
その成果を...
I'll show the results of...
サラマンダーとして生きてきた
living as a salamander.
が、人間社会にわしこれくらい溶け込めますよ、と成果を、おぬしらにお見せしようと
But I want to show you all how well I can blend into human society...
思いますのじゃ
...or so I thought.
ここで、おぬしらに...
Now, to you all...
おぬしら、やっぱ、仮面外してほしい？
Do you guys really want me to take off my mask?
お面、お面外してほしい？
Do you want me to take off the mask?
見たいのじゃ？見たい？
Do you want to see? Do you want to see it?
見たい？
Do you want to see?
見たい？どうなのじゃ？
Do you want to see? What do you say?
見たかったら、高評価してほしいのじゃ。お願いなのじゃ。人間してほしいのじゃ。
If you want to see, leave a Like. Please. Be human about it!
人間してほしいのじゃ
Please show some humanity.
いい？して？
Okay? Will you do it?
うん、してる？した？
Yeah, are you doing it? Did you?
やったのじゃー！
Yay, you did it!
２回は押さなくていいのじゃ。なくなっちゃう。１回だけ押してほしいのじゃ。
Don't press it twice, it'll cancel it. Just once, please!
うん、もうしてる？した？
Yeah, already done? Did you?
やったのじゃー！奇数、奇数回を押してほしいのじゃ。
Yay! Please press it an odd number of times.
よし、じゃあ、おぬしらが一杯高評価してくれたみたいじゃから
Okay, since you guys gave me plenty of Likes,
わしも、お面を外して
I will take off my mask...
ゲームを始めるとしますのじゃー！
...and start the game!
ちょっと遅かった。ちょっと遅かった。
A bit too slow. A bit too slow.
ちょっと遅かったのじゃ。
That was a bit slow.
よいしょ。にょ。
There we go. Nyo.
どうじゃろうか。音でかいかの？
How is it? Is the sound too loud?
BGMの音量とかがどうかをおぬしらに聞きたいんじゃが
I want to ask you guys about the BGM volume.
おっきい？
Is it loud?
これぐらいなら、いい？
Is it okay like this?
ちっちゃい？
Is it too quiet?
バランスどうなのじゃ？そもそも聞こえておるかの？
How is the balance? Can you hear it at all?
どうかの？
How is it?
元のBGM残ってる？は！
Is the original BGM still playing? Ah!
どう？戻せた。これでいいんじゃない？
How is it? I fixed it. Isn't this fine?
これで、これでいいんじゃない？どうなのじゃ？直った？
Isn't this fine? What do you think? Fixed?
これいいんじゃない？どうじゃ、どうじゃ。ちっちゃい？
Isn't this good? How is it? Too quiet?
態度が小さい？え、それはいいことなのじゃ。
Is my attitude small? Oh, that's a good thing!
それいいんじゃない？
Isn't that great?
いい感じ？いい感じ？いい感じそうかの？
Is it good? Good? Does it seem good?
ちょっとあの、まだ新人のうちは、ちょっとこういうのいっぱいおぬしらに聞くかもしれないけど
Since I'm still a rookie, I might ask you guys a lot of questions like this...
教えてくれると嬉しいですのじゃ。
...but I'd be happy if you could help me out.
態度でかくしてほしい？でも空気読めないよ、そしたら。
Do you want me to act big? But then I wouldn't be able to read the room.
空気を読むためには、やはり、謙虚に行かなきゃいけない？
To read the room, after all, do I need to remain humble?
どうかの？
What do you think?
よし、それじゃあ、空気読みを...
Alright, then, let's start Kuuki Yomi...
ゲームBGMちょっとちっちゃい？了解なのじゃ。むむむ。
Is the game BGM a bit quiet? Understood. Hmm...
どう？でかすぎ？あげすぎ？
How is it? Too loud? Raised too much?
あ、消えた。
Oh, it went away.
あげすぎ？いい感じ？
Too high? Or is it good?
いい感じ。よし！
Perfect. Alright!
それじゃあ、わしの空気読み、行きますのじゃ！
Well then, here goes my Kuuki Yomi playthrough!
ん？どのボタンかの。これ。
Hm? Which button is it? This one.
これでいけるじゃない？
We can go with this, right?
「ここは自由に空気を読んでよい空間。あなたが空気を読むことを止める人は誰もいません」
"This is a space where you can read the situation freely. No one will stop you from reading the situation."
空気を読むことを止める人がいる空間があるのじゃ？
Is there a space where someone stops you from reading the situation?
人間社会ってむずいのじゃ。なんか、空気読むのが逆にダメ？逆の逆みたいのもあるのじゃ。トラップなのじゃ。
Human society is tough. Like, reading the situation is actually bad? There's also the opposite of the opposite. It's a trap.
「たった一人で空気が読める夢の世界。心ゆくまでご堪能下さい」なるほど。
"A dream world where you can read the situation all by yourself. Please enjoy to your heart's content." I see.
やっていくのじゃ！
Let's do this!
「画面内の赤いのを動かす事で空気を読め」赤いの？赤いの？
"Read the situation by moving the red thing on the screen." Red thing? Red thing?
「そうじゃない場合もあるが、そこは空気を読んで違う行動をとれ」
"Sometimes that's not the case, but in those times, read the situation and take a different action."
「中断したい時はESCキーを押せ」了解なのじゃ。操作方法の説明。
"Press the ESC key when you want to pause." Understood. Explanation of controls.
始まった！第１問！
It started! Question 1!
電車。ん？なに？なにが起きてるのじゃ？
A train. Hm? What? What is happening?
何が起きてるのじゃ？
What is happening?
あ！あ！あ！こういうことね！こういう、お座り系ね！あ、なるほど。
Ah! Ah! Ah! So that's what it is! This kind of seating situation! Ah, I see.
何が起きてるかを瞬時に判断しなきゃいけないんじゃな。
We have to instantly judge what is happening, right?
「小学生ドミノ世界記録に挑戦！」あ、小学生、子供のね。子供に成功体験を積ま...
"Elementary schoolers attempt a domino world record!" Ah, elementary schoolers, kids. We have to let children accumulate successful experiences...
成功体験を積めなかった子供は後になって...
Children who couldn't build successful experiences...
第３問
[Question 3]
それが一生、一生執着してしまうのじゃ。伏せ！
...will end up being obsessed with it their whole lives. Lie down!
え？人間じらされるの好きって聞いた。じらしてみるのじゃ。じら、あ、じらす、ん？
Eh? I heard humans like being teased. Let's try teasing them. Teas-, ah, tease, hm?
第４問
[Question 4]
でもこれも好きなんじゃろ、人間。こういうのが。
But humans like this too, right? This kind of thing.
そしたらさ、バカじゃん。あ、後ろに人がいる。
And then... "You guys are stupid." Ah, there's someone behind them.
え、でもこれ、わし知ってるのじゃ。右側歩いちゃダメなのじゃ。
Eh, but I know about this. You're not supposed to walk on the right side.
エスカレーターはね、歩くと危ないからね。こうすることでね、秩序を守っていますのじゃ。
Because walking on escalators is dangerous. Doing this maintains order.
第５問
[Question 5]
これは正しいと思うのじゃ。
I think this one is correct.
カモメ、あ、鳥が...
Seagull... ah, the birds...
え、これバズる。これツイッターにあげたらバズるのじゃ！
Eh, this will go viral. If I post this on Twitter, it'll go viral!
これで万バズるのじゃ。人間、人間今写真撮るのじゃ。
This will get tens of thousands of likes. Human, human, take a picture now!
写真撮って！写真撮ってツイッターあげて、50万バズらせるのじゃ。
Take a picture! Take a picture, post it on Twitter, and get 500k likes.
そこはかとなく... そこはかとなく読めてるっぽい。
[Vaguely...] It seems I can vaguely read it.
これ褒められた？わし。わし褒められた？
Was I praised for this? Was I praised?
いいってこと？
Does it mean it's good?
第６問 / いいってことかな？あの写真、万バズするじゃろうな。
[Question 6] Does it mean it's good? That picture is definitely going viral.
あ、サンタさん！
Ah, Santa Claus!
えっと、ん？ん？
Let's see, huh? Huh?
寝る。
Going to sleep.
やっぱあの、こういうのって、建前同士がね、大人も子供もそれぞれ分かち合って生きている。知らなきゃいけない。あ、次。
After all, in these situations, adults and children live by sharing their public stances. They have to know. Ah, next.
第７問
[Question 7]
ご注文は？生、生、生、生で。
What's your order? Draft beer, draft, draft, draft, please.
え？でも冷はじゃよ、今。
Wait, sake/cold drinks are fine right now.
ウーロンちゃんなのじゃ。ウーロンちゃん飲みたいのじゃ。
Oolong tea! I want to drink oolong tea.
ウーロンちゃん飲みたい。選択を押せないのじゃ。
I want to drink oolong tea. I can't select it!
どうやって選択押す？どこから押せる？
How do I select it? Where can I click?
第８問
[Question 8]
え、選択できなかった！わし悪い？サラマンダー、選べなかったのじゃ。
Eh, I couldn't select it! Am I in the wrong, Salamander? I couldn't choose.
ん？
Huh?
AちゃんとBちゃんとCちゃんがいるのじゃ。
There's A-chan, B-chan, and C-chan.
なに？あ、止まった。
What? Ah, it stopped.
第９問 / 何？何？今何が起きた？今何？何が起きたのじゃ？
[Question 9] What? What? What just happened? What now? What happened?
AちゃんとBちゃんとCちゃん。A、B、C。
A-chan, B-chan, and C-chan. A, B, C.
あ、人を選ぶ？え、選ばれない人を選ぶみたい。
Ah, choose a person? Wait, looks like I need to choose the one who isn't chosen.
でもそれは妥協だと、なんかそれは良くないのじゃ。選ばれないからという理由で選ばれた人は本当に本当に選ばれた人、嬉しくないと思うのじゃ。
But that's just a compromise, so that's not good. A person chosen just because they wouldn't normally be chosen... I don't think they'd actually feel happy about it.
第10問
[Question 10]
うれしぃちゃん？
Pleased-chan?
「この最後の１ピンを倒せたら付き合ってください」「うん、いいよ」
"If I can knock down this last pin, please go out with me." "Yeah, okay."
倒れないのじゃ！
It won't fall!
こんなんで、こんなんで自分の意志を他人に委ねるやつに、倒れることのために倒れるわけにはいかないのじゃ！
There's no way it's going to fall for someone who leaves their own decisions to fate like this!
ほんやんわりと
[Warmly...]
やっぱ、あの、自分の、他の人にね、最終的な判断を委ねるってのはね、よくないのじゃ。弱さなのじゃ。ダメなのじゃ。
After all, leaving your final decision to others is not good. It's weakness. It's no good.
そんな、そんな弱さで、そんな生半可な気持ちで付き合うって言われて、本当にCちゃんは喜ぶか？喜ばないと思うのじゃ。人間の弱さなのじゃ。
With that kind of weakness, with such half-hearted feelings, would C-chan really be happy to be asked out? I don't think she would. It's human weakness.
厳しい？厳しい？人間はこういうのもダメ？人間...
Am I being too harsh? Harsh? Is this not allowed for humans either? Humans...
えー、でも、でもそれって本当にその人のためになるのかな？なんか、わし思うんじゃが、わし思うんじゃが...
But does that really benefit the person? Well, I think... I really think...
偉いけどゲーム違う？そっか。ゲームの趣旨みたいなのもある？
That's admirable, but isn't this a different game? I see. Does this game have a specific purpose too?
むずいのじゃ。でもここ、ここでゲームだからと言って自分の意志を曲げてしまったら、それが一生続いちゃう気がするのじゃ。
This is hard. But if I bend my will here just because it's a game, I feel like I'll keep doing it for the rest of my life.
なんかワールドトリガーで言ってたのじゃ。ワールドトリガーでこんなセリフがあった気がするのじゃ。
I think they said something like this in World Trigger. I feel like there was a line like this in World Trigger.
1回でも曲げちゃダメなのじゃ。次行くのじゃ！よし。
You must never bend it, not even once. Moving on!
第11問
[Question 11]
行くのじゃ。
Here I go.
これ何？何か流れてきた。
What's this? Something's rolling in.
えいっ！ん、潰す系？
Hah! Wait, is it a crushing type?
えいっ！これ、目押しゲーってこと？
Hah! Wait, does this mean it's a rhythm/timing game?
えいっ！何これ目押しゲー？
Hah! What is this timing game?
これ何が正しいのじゃ？これ何？目押しゲー？ゲーム、ミニゲーム入ったのじゃ。
What's the correct answer here? What is this timing game? Oh, a mini-game started.
第12問
[Question 12]
のじゃ。
I see.
起立！はい。礼、礼。着席。
Rise! Yes. Bow, bow. Be seated.
これは、和を乱してはいけないのじゃ。人間社会。
You shouldn't disrupt the harmony here. Human society.
第13問 / 彼女と動物園に来ました
[Question 13]
デート？のじゃ。
A date? I see.
何？「禁」って書いてるのじゃ。
What? It says "Prohibited".
「禁」って書いてるのじゃ。危ない？
It says "Prohibited". Is it dangerous?
第14問
[Question 14]
ん？
Huh?
カチカチ。スマホ見てるのじゃ。幽霊寂しがってる。かまってあげよう。
*tap tap* He's looking at his phone. The ghost looks lonely. Let's keep her company.
うわっ！あ、驚いてあげるというやつね。幽霊にも優しい。
Whoa! Ah, so you surprise them. Kind even to ghosts.
第15問
[Question 15]
ふんふん。
Hmph hmph.
うぉ！えい、ウェーブなのじゃ、ウェーブ。こういうのめっちゃやってみたいのじゃ。
Whoa! Hah, it's a wave! I really want to try doing this.
遊びもありありやりたいのじゃ。4人だと少ないかの？
I want to join in too! Is four people too few?
4人だと少ないかの？
Is four people too few?
これ好きなのじゃ。わしもやりたい！
I like this one. I want to do it too!
わしもやりたい！
I want to play too!
ふむふむ、空気読みわかってきた。「ほどよく読めてる」っぽい。
Hmm, I'm getting the hang of this. It says I'm "considerate."
え？これわし、わしなかなか、わしなかなか…
What? I guess I'm actually...
あの、人間社会でやっていけそうじゃない？
...pretty good at getting along in human society, aren't I?
人間社会でやっていけそうな感じするのじゃ。
I feel like I could make it in human society.
任せるのじゃ。
Leave it to me.
第16問
[Question 16]
16問。
Question 16.
雨降っている。
It's raining.
傘さしてる。
Holding an umbrella.
あ、こういう系ね、よける系。
Ah, this type of situation where you have to avoid others.
わしこういうのめっちゃよけるのじゃ。
I'm really good at dodging these things.
傘の先っちょって怖くない？
Aren't umbrella tips scary?
傘の先っちょ怖いから、
Umbrella tips are scary, so...
傘持つときは、下に向けて持ってるのじゃ。
...when I hold one, I keep it pointed downwards.
次のバス停でおりる僕です。
"I'm getting off at the next bus stop." Oh, it's a bus stop.
第17問
[Question 17]
終点。終点なら押さなくていいのじゃ。
The last stop. You don't need to press the button if it's the last stop.
終点なら押さなくていいのじゃ。
You don't need to press it if it's the last stop.
のじゃ。
Indeed.
第18問
[Question 18]
あー、ポールある系ね。
Ah, the pole is there.
ポールあるならどかないかもなのじゃ。
If there's a pole to hold onto, maybe they won't move.
ポールなかったらどくけど、ポールあったら…ん？
If there wasn't a pole, I'd move. But since there is one... Huh?
いや、わしが左にずれればよかったのでは？気づかなかった。
Wait, shouldn't I have shifted to the left? I didn't realize.
デートだってデート。
It's a date! A date!
あ、おなごは恋愛映画が見たいけど、わしはロボットアニメが見たい？
Oh, the girl wants to see a romance movie, but I want to see a robot anime?
えー？あ、ああ！
What? Ah! Oh!
優柔不断になってたら、どちらにもどちらにも行けなく…
If I hesitate, we won't be able to go to either...
第20問
[Question 20]
あ、なんかおなごが車道側歩いてる。
Ah, the girl is walking on the side of the road.
でもわし、わしも怖いから、そのときは一緒に受け入れよう。
But I'm scared too, so let's just accept it together.
諦めよう。
Let's give up.
むずい！空気読みむずいのじゃ！
It's so hard! Reading the room is so hard!
むずい、むずい！
It's hard, it's hard!
どう？どう？
How is it? How is it?
え、だってわしさ、これサラマンダーあるあるなんじゃが、
Well, for me, this is a total Salamander thing, but...
あの、電車のね、ホーム歩くときね、電車側怖いから、
...when walking on a train platform, the train side is scary...
できるだけ、中側通りたいのじゃ。
...so I want to walk on the inside.
車道でも同様、できるだけ、信号待つときも、
Same goes for the road, even when waiting at a crosswalk...
できるだけ車道側じゃない奥の方で待つんじゃが、
...I try to wait as far back as possible from the road.
ちょっと怖いのじゃ、怖いのじゃ。
Because it's a bit scary, it's scary.
もう、駄目なときは駄目なのじゃ。諦めるのじゃ。
When it's impossible, it's just impossible. You have to give up.
次なのじゃ。
Next one.
第21問
[Question 21]
21問。
Question 21.
あ、おはようございます。あ、あ、
Ah, good morning. Ah, ah...
あ、これ、これは、あの、
Ah, this... this is...
第22問
[Question 22]
反応しちゃうと、社内政治が危うい。わし知ってるのじゃ！
If I react, office politics get dangerous. I know this!
あ、目に入らんのか！入ります、入ります！
Oh, "Is it not in your sight?" Yes, it is! It is!
いくらでもへりくだり、自分が下ですと、
I'll humble myself as much as needed and say I'm below you.
後輩ムーブをかますのじゃ。やはり人間社会で生き残る…
I will pull off the ultimate junior move. To survive in human society...
第23問
[Question 23]
歩くの早いのじゃ。お主、お主、
You're walking fast. Hey, hey!
お主、歩く速度合わせるのじゃ。
Hey, match my walking speed!
車道側は嫌じゃけど、歩く速度ぐらいは、いくらでも合わせるのじゃ。
I don't like the roadside, but I can easily match your walking speed.
第24問
[Question 24]
今日はデートです。そろそろ彼氏と思っていいのかな。え、彼氏じゃないのにデートなのじゃ？
"Today is a date. Is it okay to think of him as my boyfriend?" Wait, you're dating but you aren't boyfriend and girlfriend?
アニメを見に行こうとするので、恋愛映画にさせましたが、
"He tried to go see an anime, so I made him watch a romance movie instead."
「男の子って本当空気読めない。」「彼ったら勇気出して手を繋いできた。」
"Boys really can't read the room." "Then, he gathered his courage and held my hand."
「もう私たちは付き合ってるよね。」それはどうなのじゃ？そして？
"We're already dating, right?" I wonder about that. And then?
ちゅーしてる、ちゅー。あ、こういうこと？
They're kissing! Kissing! Ah, like this?
いい、いい空気にしちゃう的な？
Setting a nice mood?
え、恋愛映画見てこれするの本当にいるの？本当にこういうのあるの？
Wait, do people really do this while watching a romance movie? Does this really happen?
第25問
[Question 25]
知らないのじゃ。え、え、なんかちゅーしてるのじゃ。え、
I wouldn't know. Oh, they're kissing. Uh...
見、見ないふり。見ないふり。気づかないふり、
Pretend, pretend not to look. Pretend not to look. Pretend not to notice...
のじゃ。
...indeed.
え、でも、ガン見してやってもよかったな。ガン見してやってもよかったのじゃ。
But maybe I should have just stared at them. I should have stared at them.
公道ですよ、公道ですよ、お主ら。お主らここは公道ですって言って。
This is a public road! This is a public road, you two! Tell them, "This is a public road!"
公の、公の道路ですよって言って。ガン見してやっても。
Say, "This is a public street." Even staring at them...
ぶつかる？ぶつかる、そこまでは、そこまで別に悪いことされたわけじゃないし、
Bump into them? No, that's going too far. It's not like they did anything bad to me.
ぶつかるのは、炎上しちゃうのじゃ。
Bumping into them would cause a massive backlash.
もしその、カップルを公道でちゅーしてるカップルいてワロタっていう動画を撮って
What if some malicious person took a video saying, "Look at this couple kissing in public, lol,"
Twitterにあげてる悪いやつがいたとして、わしがそこにぶつかってったら大炎上ですのじゃ。
...and posted it on Twitter, and I happened to bump into them? It would go viral!
じゃから、よくないのじゃ。
So, that's bad.
ぶつからないのじゃ。人にぶつからないように、
I shouldn't bump into them. I try not to bump into people.
わしとか特にね、ぶつかったら燃えちゃうしね、炎で。
Especially since I'm on fire, I'll literally burn them.
尻尾がね、ぶつかったりもしちゃうから、すごい気をつけようと思いますのじゃ。
Also, my tail might hit them, so I'll make sure to be very careful.
つづりがいた？なんかさ、昨日からさ、コメント欄に先輩とかが
"Tsuzuri was here?" Lately, I've been seeing people in the comments saying...
いらっしゃったみたいなさ、めっちゃ聞くんじゃけどさ、
...that my seniors were in the chat, but...
わしがさ、いつも画面にさ、集中してるときでさ、見つけられないんじゃが。
...I'm always so focused on the screen that I can never find them.
どうしたらよいのじゃ？
What should I do?
なんかホロメンだけ名前の色ビカビカのレインボーとかにできないの？
Can't we make Holomem names flash in a rainbow color or something?
ビカビカのレインボーとかだったら大丈夫なんじゃが
If it was a flashing rainbow, it would be fine, but...
同じ色じゃからわかんないのじゃ。そっか。
...since it's the same color, I can't tell them apart. I see.
あ、いた！つづりなのじゃ！
Ah, there! It's Tsuzuri!
つづり！
Tsuzuri!
わしの人間適応力を恐れおののきながら見るが良いのじゃ！
Watch in awe and terror at my human adaptability!
第26問
[Question 26]
どこどこ？「誰がイエロー役をやってくれるかな？」
Where, where? "Who will play the yellow ranger?"
え、はいはいはい！やるやるやるやる！
Eh, yes, yes, yes! I'll do it, I'll do it!
イエローと言えば、イエローと言えば食いしん坊！なんかそういうイメージがあるのじゃ。違うかの？
Speaking of yellow, yellow is always the glutton! That's the image I have. Am I wrong?
なんで皆あげないのじゃ？オーディションって…
Why is nobody raising their hand? In an audition...
イエロー！じゃーん！かっこいい！爆発なのじゃー！
Yellow! Ta-da! So cool! An explosion!
レンジャー演出なのじゃー！
It's a ranger special effect!
わしレンジャーもちょっと見てたよ。なんじゃっけ、ゲキレンジャー？
I used to watch rangers a bit too. What was it, Gekiranger?
おにゃん？ん？ん？
Onyan? Hm? Hm?
何？
What is it?
テトリスなのじゃ。
It's Tetris.
これで合ってる？
Is this right?
合ってる？
Is it right?
のじゃ？
Really?
ん？これ違ったの？合ってるの？え？のじゃ？
Hm? Was that wrong? Or was it right? Eh? Really?
脳内占いで君のを見てあげるね。わー楽しみ♪
"Let me check yours with a brain reading." "Wow, I can't wait!"
あ、なんか占いコンテンツ。は！
Ah, a fortune-telling thing. Ha!
まあ人間とは繁殖を望む個体もいると聞くから
Well, since I hear some humans desire reproduction...
そんなにおかしいことじゃないのでは。
...I don't think it's that strange.
ないかと、思うのじゃ。
Or so I think.
長生き。
Long life.
右向け右！ふん。
Right face, right! Hm.
え、合ってる？右？
Eh? Is that right? Right?
なんとななしに、読めてるっぽい。ふむふむ。
Somehow... seems like I'm reading it. Mmhmm.
ふむふむふむ。
Mmhmm, mmhmm.
いけるのじゃ。
I can do this.
なんかいけそう。わしなんか、え、これ左？なんで？
I think I can do it. Wait, is this left? Why?
は！ん？
Ha! Hm?
わしから見て右、ん？
From my perspective, right... hm?
わしから見て…右？
From my perspective... right?
は、おぬしから見ると…
But from your perspective...
ん？左？ん？
Hm? Left? Hm?
んーーーー。
Hmmmmm...
次いくのじゃ！
Let's move on!
ん、むずいのじゃ。
Hm, it's hard.
お前。
You.
バーバー、バー。バーバーってなんなのじゃ？
Barber, bar. What on earth is a barber?
バーバー？バーバーって何？
Barber? What's a barber?
バー。バーバーって、床屋？
Bar. Is a barber... a barbershop?
何？のじゃ。
What is it? Seriously.
第32問
[Question 32]
あ！あ！これやりたい！ねえこれやりたい！
Ah! Ah! I want to do this! Hey, I want to do this!
ああああ！遅い！遅い！遅い！遅い！
Aaaah! Too slow! Too slow! Too slow! Too slow!
は！瞬発力。かっこいいって思ったら、かっこいいのじゃって思ったら… 時が…あ！
Ha! My reaction speed... I thought it was cool, I was thinking "How cool!" but...
君が手術に勝てるように明日の試合ホームランを打つぞ。
"I'll hit a home run in tomorrow's game so you can get through surgery."
ん？
Hm?
来た！
Here it comes!
ドミニカの大砲、デラサ…
Dominican cannon, De La Rosa...
のじゃー！あ！
...it is! Ah!
第34問
[Question 34]
わしのプレイスキルが低いあまりに、気持ち的には…
My play skill is so low that, emotionally...
あ！あ！あ！は！は！は！は！は！
Ah! Ah! Ah! Ha! Ha! Ha! Ha! Ha!
第35問
[Question 35]
なんかプレイスキル、あの、空気読む気、空気読む気あり！
My play skill is... wait, I have the will to read the atmosphere!
空気読む気大ありなのに、あの…プレイスキルが…
Even though I totally want to read the atmosphere, my play skill...
これが最後のボールだ。絶対に当てなくちゃ。
"This is the last ball. I must hit it."
来た！来た！来るぞ！よいしょ！
Here it comes! It's coming! Yoisho!
むずいのじゃ。
It's hard.
そして？そして？
And then? And then?
ああ、むずいのじゃ。なんか、なんか…
Ah, it's hard. Somehow, somehow...
空気読む気、気持ち、気持ちはあるのに！
I have the intention, the feeling, I have the feeling!
気持ちはあるのに！気持ちはあるのに！
I have the feeling! I have the feeling!
あの、届かない。あと一歩が。
But it doesn't reach. Just one more step.
あと一歩が届かない。判断が遅い、のじゃ！
One more step is out of reach. My judgment is slow!
行くのじゃ。
Moving on.
むずいのじゃ。
It's hard.
あ！あ！苦手なやつ。いくよ、いくよ。よいしょ！
Ah! Ah! My weak point. Here I go, here I go. Yoisho!
ああ。
Ah.
第37問
[Question 37]
苦手なのじゃ。なわとび、大繩跳び。
I'm bad at this. Jump rope, double dutch.
あ、す、座ります。
Ah, I- I'll sit down.
夜露死苦。
Yoroshiku. (Best regards)
第38問
[Question 38]
ふん。
Hm.
まだやれるのじゃ。何？あ！
I can still do this. What? Ah!
打球、打球、打球…ん？何？ん？
Hitting the ball, hitting the ball, hitting the ball... Hm? What? Hm?
第39問
[Question 39]
な、な、な、今のはわし何するべきじゃった？
Wh- Wh- Wh- What was I supposed to do just now?
寝てる。寝てる。あ、逃げる。
Sleeping. Sleeping. Ah, move away.
逃げる、逃げる、逃げる、逃げる、逃げる、逃げる。
Move, move, move, move, move, move.
あ、立ってる。座る、座る、座る。
Ah, standing up. Sit, sit, sit.
第40問
[Question 40]
寄りかかんないで、燃えちゃう。燃えちゃうのじゃ。
Don't lean on me, you'll burn. You'll burn!
お手を拝借、よ〜〜お、ポン！
Hands ready! Yo~~~ Clap!
ちょっと遅い？
A bit slow?
瞬発力が、瞬発力が…
My reaction speed... My reaction speed...
収罰力がないのじゃ。違う、
I have no discipline power... No, wait,
音ゲー？音ゲーむがしい？
Rhythm games? Are rhythm games hard?
プレイスキル自信なし。
I have no confidence in my playing skills.
なんかいつもちょっと遅いんじゃ。でも気持ちは、気持ちは
I'm always a little slow. But the spirit, the spirit...
あるし、何やるかはわかるんじゃけど。
is there, and I know what to do...
リズム天国心配になってきたのじゃ。
I'm starting to get worried about Rhythm Heaven.
キャボの歌からやりたいけど、心配になってきたのじゃ。
I want to start with the DJ School song, but I'm getting worried.
第41問
Question 41
あ！スカートの中見えちゃって危ない。え、ね、あれ？どう？
Ah! The inside of her skirt is visible! That's dangerous! Wait, what do I do?
あ、危ないよ。スカート隠すのじゃ。スカートの中見えちゃう。
Ah, it's dangerous! Cover up the skirt. The inside of her skirt will be seen.
女の子電車の中寝る時危ないのじゃ。
It's dangerous when girls sleep on the train.
第42問
Question 42
今日は大好きなアイドル「A子」の握手会だ…
Today is the handshake event for my favorite idol, 'A-ko'...
いや、これで帰るのはA子に、全員に対して失礼じゃろ。
No, leaving like this would be rude to A-ko, actually, to everyone.
これでB子の人気がないからってB子に行ったら、それは失礼じゃろ。
If you go to B-ko just because she isn't popular, that's rude.
演者に対して。本気でやってるんじゃから。
Rude to the performer, who is doing her best.
第43問。何？何？何？あ、大きくなるキノコ。ジャンプ、ジャンプ。
Question 43. What? What? What? Ah, a mushroom that makes you big. Jump, jump.
人間、一緒の、思いやり、足並みを揃えて。
Humans, together, with consideration, keeping in step.
第44問
Question 44
カメラ撮ってる。何でそんなアングルなのじゃ？
Taking a photo. Why is the angle like that?
何でそんなアングル、のじゃ？ん？何が起きているの？
Why that angle? Hmm? What's happening?
第45問。何が起きていたの？
Question 45. What was happening?
「この部屋少し寒くない？」「了解」
"Isn't this room a bit cold?" "Roger that."
寒いから上げるのじゃ。温度。上げ、上げ、上げ、上げ。
Since it's cold, let's turn it up. The temperature. Up, up, up, up.
どれくらいが良いんじゃろな、寒いって。これくらいかの。
What's a good temperature when someone is cold? Around here?
なんとなく…読めてるっぽい。
Somehow... it seems they got it.
なるほどなのじゃ。分かってきた。分かってきた。え、暑い？
I see. I'm starting to understand. I get it. Oh, is it hot?
どれくらい、どれくらいに上げるのが良いのじゃ？
What temperature should I raise it to?
ん？冷房、切るの、あ、切れば良かったのかな？
Hmm? The AC... turn it off? Ah, maybe I should have turned it off?
上げないで、切れば良かったのかな？
Instead of turning it up, maybe turning it off was better?
人間の適正温度が分かんないのじゃ。人間はどれくらいの温度だと心地良いか分かんないのじゃ。
I don't know the comfortable temperature for humans. I don't know what temperature makes humans feel comfortable.
いっつもわし基準で部屋の温度設定しておるから、サラマンダーには分かんないのじゃ。その辺は、
Since I always set the room temperature based on myself, a salamander wouldn't know. That kind of thing...
人間の体のこと、もうちょっと勉強しなきゃいけんの。
I need to study more about the human body.
行くのじゃ。第46問。
Let's go. Question 46.
週刊誌。本読んでる。あ、邪魔じゃって。よいしょ、よいしょ。
Weekly Magazine. They're reading a book. Oh, you're in the way. There we go, there we go.
立ち読みめっちゃいるのじゃ。立ち読みって良いの？
There are so many people reading on their feet. Is standing and reading allowed?
第47問。
Question 47.
あ、子供に成功体験を積ませるのじゃ！
Ah! Let the children gain some success experience!
成功体験って大事なのじゃ。第48問。
Success experiences are important. Question 48.
「あー、のどかわいたー。ついでにコーヒー買ってきてよ」「了解」
"Ah, I'm thirsty. Can you buy some coffee while you're at it?" "Roger that."
コーヒー。のどかわ、暑そう。でもホットしかないよ。
Coffee. Thirsty... she looks hot. But there's only hot coffee.
でも女の子は、言う通りにしなかったら怒るから、コールドのものを買っても意味ないのじゃ。コーヒーって言ったよねって絶対に言われるのじゃ。
But girls get mad if you don't do exactly what they say, so buying something cold is useless. She'll definitely say, "I said coffee, didn't I?"
第49問。熱いのも絶対に怒られるから、それはもう覚悟、覚悟をするのじゃ。
Question 49. She will also definitely get mad if it's hot, so I must prepare myself for that.
ちょ、肉、肉、取る。店員さんが。
Wait, the meat, I'll take the meat. The waiter...
よいしょ。よいしょ。あ、この子にあげよう。お主、あげるよ。
There we go. There we go. Ah, I'll give it to this girl. Here, for you.
第50問。女の子何してもキレるから、とりあえず言う通りを優先にするのじゃ。
Question 50. Since girls get mad no matter what you do, you should just prioritize doing exactly what they say for now.
緊急特番！驚異の気功術！！あー。
Emergency Special! Marvelous Qigong Technique!! Ah...
うわーー！
Whoa!
そこはかとなく…読めてるっぽい。エンタメが分かるサラマンダーじゃろ。まあ、わし、VTuberじゃからの。エンタメに強い、エンタメに強いのじゃ。
Somehow... it seems they got it. I'm a salamander who understands entertainment. Well, I am a VTuber, after all. I'm good at entertainment, very good at it.
え、何してもキレるのじゃ。キレる時は何してもキレるから、
What, she'll get mad no matter what? When they're in a bad mood, they'll get mad no matter what,
2個買うのが本当はいいのじゃ。冷たいのとコーヒーも両方買うのじゃ。
so the best thing is actually to buy both. Buy a cold drink and a coffee.
やらせ？いや、見てるお主らが楽しい方が良いのじゃ。楽しませられた人が勝ちなのじゃ。
Staged? No, it's better if you viewers are having fun. The one who entertains wins.
行くのじゃ。第51問。
Let's go. Question 51.
何？え？それも良くないのじゃ。それは本当に良くないのじゃ。今の御時世、もっと良くないのじゃ。ちょ、ちょ、ちょ。
What? Eh? That is also not good. That is really not good. In this day and age, it's even worse. Wait, wait, wait.
気を付けるのじゃ。炎上しちゃう。火の用心じゃ、火の用心じゃ！だ、だ、ダメなのじゃ！
Be careful. You'll get canceled. Watch out for fire, watch out for fire! No, no, that's bad!
第52問。何？あ。
Question 52. What? Ah.
ちょ、ちょ、何見とるん？な、何なのじゃ。
Wait, what are you looking at? Wh-What's going on?
第53問。人間、人間、人の視界、視界を。
Question 53. Humans, humans, human line of sight, line of sight...
何？あ、泥が、泥が。ちょっと止まる。
What? Ah, the mud, the mud. Stop for a bit.
人間にかけちゃう。良くないのじゃ。でも後ろも困るかな、閊えて。
Splashing humans is bad. But it might trouble the car behind if I get stuck.
よいしょ。よいしょ、よいしょ。
There we go. There we go, there we go.
ふむふむふむふむ...
Hmm, hmm, hmm...
何？「お兄ちゃん、おなかすいた」
What? "Big brother, I'm hungry..."
「お兄ちゃんがなんとかするからがんばるんだぞ」
"Big brother will do something about it, so hang in there."
あみだ大会決勝！勝ったほうが焼肉食べ放題！
Amida lottery tournament finals! The winner gets all-you-can-eat yakiniku!
線は書いても書かなくてもいい。うわ。
"You can draw a line or not." Whoa.
えーっと、今、今はちょっと待って。計算ができない。
Uh, wait, wait a second. I can't calculate.
「兄」ん？ん？どうなる？
"Big brother," hm? Hm? What's going to happen?
待って、待って！ちょ、もうちょっとゆっくり！ゆっくり考えさせて！
Wait, wait! Ch- Give me a little more time! Let me think!
1、2、3、4。あ、引く、引く、引くといい。引くといい。
1, 2, 3, 4. Oh, drawing, drawing, drawing a line would be good.
よし、よし、よし、よし！よし、よし！いや、むずいのじゃ。考えるのむずいのじゃ。
Alright, alright, alright! Yes, yes! No, this is hard. Thinking is hard.
当たったかな？当たったかの？ちょっとむずいのじゃ、こういう処理能力、自信なし。
Did I get it? Did I get it? It's a bit hard, I have no confidence in this kind of processing.
え？何？なんか恥ずかしがってる。
Eh? What? He looks embarrassed about something.
ん？止める的な？あ、隠してあげる的な？
Hm? Like stopping it? Oh, like hiding it for him?
これ？あ！
This? Ah!
さっきできなかったやつ、それか！さっき腕がないのってそれか！
The one I couldn't do earlier, is that it?! The one with no arms earlier, is that what it was?!
理解したのじゃ。むずかしい。これゲームなのじゃ、ゲーム。
I understand now. So hard. This is a game, a game.
ふむ、ふむ、ふむ。あからさまに。え、あからさまにってかなり、かなり読めてる説ない？
Hmm, hmm, hmm. "Visibly..." Eh, doesn't "visibly" mean there's a strong chance I'm reading it really well?
わし、すごいんじゃない？わし、サラムンダーとは思えんのじゃない？もうまるで人間。
Am I not amazing? You wouldn't think I'm a Salamander, would you? Just like a human.
まるで人間なんじゃなかろうかと思うんじゃが。ふむ、ふむ。
I'm starting to think I might be just like a human. Hmm, hmm.
わかってきたのじゃ。かなり、かなりなの。
I'm starting to get it. Quite, quite a bit.
出たのじゃ。てれん。何？
It came out! Ta-da. What?
何これ？ゴミ？ゴミ捨てるのじゃ。ゴミ、どうやって捨てるのがいいのかな？
What is this? Trash? Toss the trash away. What's the best way to discard trash?
あ、隠れた。あ、下に隠しちゃうタイプ？
Oh, it's hidden. Ah, the type that hides it underneath?
なんかさ、消しカスとかさ、下に隠すとどんどん溜まっていくのじゃ。
Like eraser shavings... if you hide them underneath, they just keep accumulating.
「すごい美味しいお店...」あ、あ、女の子怒ってる、怒ってる！ちょ、起きて、起きて！
"A really delicious restaurant..." Ah, ah, the girl is mad! She's mad! Hey, wake up!
起きて、起きて、起きて！あ、あ、うん、言うのか。よし、よし、よし、うん、うん、うん。
Wake up, wake up, wake up! Ah, ah, say "yeah"? Okay, okay, okay, yeah, yeah, yeah.
僕が悪いよ、僕が悪い。もう俺が悪い、俺が全て、俺が全て悪いです！
It's my fault, it's my fault. I'm in the wrong, I'm... I'm entirely to blame!
ごめんなのじゃ、ごめんなのじゃ、すいませんのじゃ。もう何を言われても平謝り。
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, my apologies. No matter what is said, just flat-out apologize.
平謝りすればおなごの機嫌は直る。直らなくても、平謝りしない方がより最悪な結果になるのじゃ。
If you apologize profusely, her mood will improve. Even if it doesn't, not apologizing will only lead to a worse outcome.
でかい、でかい、でかい。
It's loud, loud, loud.
でもわかるのじゃ。曲って、音ってでかければでかいほどよくて。
But I get it. Music, sound... the louder the better.
音ってでかければでかいほど良いんじゃが、外じゃとね、迷惑じゃからね。
The louder the sound, the better it is, but outside, it's a nuisance.
家で聞く分にはね、でかければでかいほど。
For listening at home, the louder the better.
「今日はプレミアムフライデー」ふむ。
"Today is Premium Friday." Hmm.
ん？あ、わしが偉い人？15時？
Hm? Oh, I'm the boss? 3:00 PM?
はい、帰るよ、帰るよ。
Alright, I'm going home, going home.
偉い人が帰んないと部下は帰れないというのじゃ。
If the boss doesn't go home, the subordinates can't go home.
でも15時って早いの。
But 3:00 PM is early.
「今日は彼女とデートだ」牛。
"Today is a date with my girlfriend." A cow.
ん？焼肉行きたいのじゃ。
Hm? I want to go to yakiniku.
お寿司怖いのじゃ、濡れてるし。
Sushi is scary because it's wet.
ふむ。
Hmm.
そこはかとなく。そこはかとなく、読めてるっぽい。
Vaguely. "Vaguely... seems like they can read the air."
ふむ、なかなか。なかなかいいんじゃなかろうか。
Hmm, quite. Isn't that quite good?
ふむ、ふむ。のじゃ。ん？おし？ん？ん？ん？
Hmm, hmm. Yeah. Hm? Sushi? Hm? Hm? Hm?
のじゃ。焼肉食べたいのじゃ。好きなのじゃ。
Yeah. I want to eat yakiniku. I love it.
行くのじゃ！第61問
Here we go! Question 61.
あ！あ！あ！
Ah! Ah! Ah!
不可抗力、逃げられない。のじゃ！
Force majeure, I can't escape. Here!
あ、あ、止めまくっちゃだめみたい。食べたいのだけ食べよう。
Ah, ah, looks like you shouldn't keep stopping it. Let's just eat what we want.
サーモン！タマゴ好き。エビは食べない。
Salmon! I love egg. I won't eat shrimp.
これも知らないから食べない。タマゴ好きなのじゃ！
I don't know what this is, so I won't eat it. I love egg!
あと何じゃ？サーモンとタマゴだけ食べるのじゃ。ふむ。
What else? I'll only eat salmon and egg. Hmm.
「お手を拝借」来た！
"Clap your hands," here it comes!
よーーーーぉ、ぽん！あ、おって、ぬ、ぬ、ぬ...
Ready... *clap*! Ah, wait, n-n-n...
ずるなのじゃ！これ人間がずる、人間がわるいのじゃ！
That's cheating! The human is cheating, the human is in the wrong!
「お前の弁当温め中」あ、あるあるなのじゃ。
"Heating your bento..." Ah, that's a classic.
これはね、横に避けてあげるとね、いいのじゃ。
In this situation, if you step aside, it's good.
行くのじゃ。
Here we go.
あ、歌ってる。あ、盛り上がるよ。盛り上がるよ。
Ah, they're singing. Ah, we're getting hyped! Getting hyped!
ん？盛り上がれない。あれ？
Hm? I can't get hyped. Huh?
何？何？「帰ってきたぜ鳥取ー！」のじゃ！
What? What? "I'm back, Tottori!" Yes!
「砂丘サイコー！」のじゃ！
"The sand dunes are awesome!" Yes!
「サハラよりデカイ！」いや、言い過ぎなのじゃ。
"Bigger than the Sahara!" No, that's an exaggeration.
いや、言い過ぎだめなのじゃ。言い過ぎなの、だめなのじゃ。
No, exaggerating is bad. Exaggerating too much is bad.
持ち上げすぎなのじゃ。
That's overhyping it.
「今日は彼女とデートだ！」ガンダムの見た目してる。
"Today is a date with my girlfriend!" She looks like a Gundam.
ロボットアニメ見るのじゃ。これは演者が悪いのじゃ。
Let's watch a robot anime. The performer is in the wrong here.
さっきの演者が悪いのじゃ。ノリづらいこという演者は良くないのじゃ。
The performer from earlier is the bad one. A performer who says hard-to-vibe things is no good.
あ、もう...
Ah, already...
のこと考えてないのじゃ？ほどよく読めてるっぽい。
...not thinking about it? It seems you're doing okay at reading the room.
うん。なかなかいいんじゃなかろうか。
Yeah, that's not bad at all.
第66問
[Question 66]
え、頭でか。
Huh, his head is huge.
ちょ、失礼します、失礼します、失礼します、お邪魔...
Wait, excuse me, excuse me, excuse me, sorry to bother...
一番後ろの席、一番後ろの席取るのじゃ。ってデカいのじゃ！デカいのじゃ！
I'll take the very back seat. But it's huge! It's too big!
第67問
[Question 67]
先頭。え、シャアいる、シャア。
The front. Oh, Char is there! Char!
赤い、赤いの。あ、でもシャアが後ろにいるということは...
The red one, the red one. Oh, but since Char is behind me, that means...
シャア専用じゃないのに乗るのじゃ。乗るのじゃ。
I should ride the one that isn't Char's custom suit. I'll get in.
第68問
[Question 68]
お前！後ろの敵何とかして！了解のじゃ！
"Hey! Deal with the enemy behind us!" Roger that!
あれ？
Huh?
えい、えい、えい！えい、えい、えい、えい！
Take that, take that! Take that, take that, take that!
わしのプレイ... きゃーーー！
My gameplay... Kyaaaaa!
あ！いけた！いけたんじゃない？
Ah! I did it! Didn't I?
第69問、のじゃ！
[Question 69] Yes!
上映中。
Showing...
あ？
Ah?
あ！
Ah!
第70問。スタンディングオベーションなのじゃ。
[Question 70] It's a standing ovation.
あ、はははは。あー、
Ah, hahaha. Ah...
渋いのじゃ、カッコいいのじゃ。なんか凄いカッコいいトークが行われるのじゃ。
How mature and cool. It looks like a very cool conversation is going on.
あからさまに...読めてるっぽい。
"Blatantly..." It seems you read the room well.
え、凄い！え、めっちゃ空気読めてて凄いのじゃ。凄いのじゃ。凄いのじゃ、凄いのじゃ。うん。
Wow, amazing! You can really read the room, that's awesome! Awesome! Truly amazing. Yeah.
うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah.
えね、わしも、わしもこれやりたい。わしもこれやりたい。わしもこれやりたい。わしも、さ、
Hey, I want to do this too. I really want to do this. I want to do this as well. At a...
シュッ。バーでさ、カッコいい大人のバーでさ、あのシュッ、「あちらのお客様からです」のやりたいのじゃ。どうしたら出来る？どうしたら出来る？
...sliding glass! At a cool, mature bar, I want to slide a glass over and say, "This is from the customer over there." How do I do that? How?
えでもさ、それをするにはさ、あの、少なくともさ、じゃあ「私投げるからあなた受け取ってね」みたいなのをさ、あの
But to do that, at the very least, you have to coordinate beforehand, like "I'm going to slide it, so you catch it"...
事前にさ、打ち合わせをしてさ、きっと事前予約のさ、なんか食べログとかで予約する時のさ、なんか備考欄とかにさ、
...and when making a reservation on Tabelog or something, in the request column, you'd have to write...
あの「シュッてやるやつをやりたいので、あの、協力していただけませんでしょうか」みたいなさ、そういうのをさ、仕込んでから行かないと、いけないんじゃないなかろうか。
...something like, "I'd like to do the sliding glass thing, so could you please cooperate?" If you don't set it up in advance like that, it won't work, right?
ダメかの。
Would that be no good?
うん。お酒飲めないのじゃ。飲めるけど、そんな強くないのじゃ。弱めではあるのじゃ。
Yeah. I can't drink alcohol. I mean, I can, but I'm not strong with it. I'm a lightweight.
だからお外では飲まないのじゃ。バーとかでも飲まないのじゃ。へろへろになっちゃうから。
So I don't drink when I'm out. I don't drink at bars either, because I'll get completely wasted.
お水飲むのじゃ。
I just drink water.
水が好きなのじゃ。水と、水とお茶が好きなのじゃ。
I like water. I like water and tea.
お家でもお酒飲まないのじゃ。なんかお友達がお酒を飲んで、深刻な相談をしたそうな時とか、
I don't drink alcohol at home either. Unless maybe a friend is drinking and wants to have a serious talk...
なんか深刻な話とかそういうので、あ、空気読み、空気読みしてますのじゃ。空気読みしてますのじゃ。
...like some serious conversation, or, oh, I'm playing Kuuki Yomi. I'm playing Kuuki Yomi.
なんか、あの、今日は、あの、辛そうな子がいたら、じゃあわしも付き合うかの、みたいなやつ？
Like, if there's someone having a hard day today, then I'll join them?
そういうのはする。え、わし超人間。わし超人間なのじゃ！
I would do that. Wow, I'm a super-considerate human! I'm an incredibly good human!
行くのじゃ。
Let's go!
うん、空気読みサラマンダーなのじゃ。
Yeah, I'm a room-reading salamander.
第71問
[Question 71]
うん。空気読みサラマンダーなのじゃ。
Yeah, I'm a room-reading salamander.
ん？何？必勝。え、なんか右でさ、右にめっちゃ見てる人いる。なんか凄いうん？
Hm? What? "Certain Victory." Wait, someone on the right is staring intently. What's this?
のじゃ？
What is it?
第72問
[Question 72]
なんでナベすっからかんなん？食べ物が届くまでもう少しの辛抱だ。
"Why is the pot empty?" "Please bear with it a bit longer until the food arrives!"
子供が、子供の未来のために、のじゃ！
For the children, for the children's future, let's go!
あああ！
Ahhhh!
第73問
[Question 73]
わしのプレイスキルが、ゲーム狂いたのばっかりに。
My gaming skills... just because of all these crazy games...
何？あ、あああ、あ、わしの、わしの...わしのプレイスキルが！
What? Ah, ahhh, my... my gaming skills!
が、がんばろうとしているのに、全然できないのじゃ！
I'm trying my best, but I can't do it at all!
第74問
[Question 74]
明日は彼女とデートだ。明日の受験で俺の人生が決まる。明日の武道館1stライブ成功しますように。
"Tomorrow is a date with my girlfriend." "Tomorrow's exam decides my life." "I hope tomorrow's Budokan live is a success."
台風、気圧なのじゃ。気圧いやじゃのう。おおおお！
It's a typhoon, the barometric pressure. I hate pressure drops. Whoa!
何、何、お前、お前、お前何しとるんじゃ！おい！おい！
What, what are you doing? Hey! Hey!
ちょちょちょちょちょ、え、え、どどどど、どうしたらいい？え？
Wait, wait, wait! What, what should I do? Huh?
はあ、の、ふ。自然災害には抗えないのじゃ。第75問。
*Sigh* We can't go against natural disasters. [Question 75]
白馬の王子様に助けてもらうことが私の夢なの。あ、いいの。
"My dream is to be saved by a prince on a white horse." Okay.
魔王の城、競馬場。競馬場、うん。
Demon King's castle, racetrack. Racetrack, yeah.
魔王の城は危ないよ。競馬も危ない？
The Demon King's castle is dangerous. Horse racing is also dangerous?
あははは！競馬場、ね、競馬場行ったことないから分かんない、競馬場行ったことない。白馬の王子...
Hahaha! I've never been to a racetrack, so I wouldn't know. A prince on a white horse...
いないの？競馬場って白馬おるの？みんなおるじゃ。競馬場いない？いないの？
No white horse? Aren't they there? No one at the racetrack?
白馬...馬？馬って言うてたよ。
White horse... Horse? They said "horse".
馬って言ってたよ。馬だろ。
They said "horse". It's a horse, right?
あ、助けてもらうのが目的だから魔王城？
Ah, is it the Demon King's castle because the goal is to be rescued?
え、あざとくない？それ、かなり。それかなり策じゃん。
Eh, isn't that quite calculated? That's quite a scheme.
確かに、ピーチ姫いつも捕まってるしな。
True, Princess Peach is always getting captured.
やっぱ、人間は、可愛い女の子を助けたい？
After all, humans want to rescue cute girls...
助けたいと思う。わしが、わしが魔王城行ったら助けてくれる？
I think they do. If I go to the Demon King's castle, will you rescue me?
わしも魔王城行こうかな？
Maybe I should go to the Demon King's castle too.
試し行動やん。
That's testing behavior!
試してるのじゃ。ねえ、助かりたいからってさ、さらわれたとかさ、不可抗力じゃなくてさ
Testing them. Hey, going to the Demon King's castle because you want to be rescued...
助かりたい、助けてもらいたいを動機でさ、あの魔王城行くのって、かなり試し、試してるのじゃ。試し行動。
rather than being kidnapped by force majeure, is totally testing them. Testing behavior.
試し行動は嫌われますのじゃ。良くないのじゃ。
Testing behavior is hated. It's not good.
良くないのじゃ。それは、うん、うん、それは、
It's not good. That is...
おぬしが悪い、のじゃ。おぬしが悪いよ。のじゃ。
your fault. It's your fault.
第76問
Question 76
行くのじゃ。
Let's go.
あ、ライブなのじゃ。よいしょ。
Ah, it's a concert. Here we go.
こういうの演者嬉しいですから。
Keep doing that, it makes the performers happy.
こういうの演者嬉しいですから。こういうね、
This kind of thing makes performers happy. This kind of...
ファンの人間、あ、あ、ファンの おぬしらがね、
human fans... ah, you fans...
一体感を持ってね、盛り上げてくれてるんだっていうのはすごい嬉しいのじゃ。
it makes us really happy to see you all getting hyped up with a sense of unity.
第77問
Question 77
仮装大会
Costume Contest
うん？
Hmm?
あ、わしの1点でいけるってやつ？でも、それはこの子の為にならないと思うのじゃ。
Ah, can we pass with my 1 point? But I don't think that would benefit this kid.
うん、ダメなものはダメなのじゃ。
No, what's bad is bad.
ひとりやってるの？点数あげてよー、あ、
He says, 'I'm doing this alone, give me points.' Ah,
あ、こういうの言ったらあげるのじゃ。
Ah, if he says this, I'll give him points.
ただーん！合格だよー！
Ta-da! You passed!
確かに、確かに。
True, true.
第78問
Question 78
こういう成功体験は別にいいのじゃ。
This kind of success story is fine.
おすなよ？絶対に押すなよ？あ、
Don't push? Absolutely don't push? Ah,
押して欲しいって？
He wants to be pushed?
第79問
Question 79
あ、熱くない。
Ah, it's not hot.
ん？
Hmm?
あつい！やめてくださいよー、熱いのじゃ熱いのじゃ熱いのじゃ！
It's hot! Please stop! It's hot, it's hot, it's hot!
どう感じているかなんて関係ないのじゃ。面白ければなんでもいいのじゃ。
How they actually feel doesn't matter. As long as it's funny, anything goes.
のじゃ、のじゃ、のじゃ、のじゃ、のじゃ。
Noja, noja, noja, noja, noja.
いくのじゃ。
Let's go.
第80問
Question 80
業界に詳しいA子さん（仮名）。何？絶対に詳しくないやろ。絶対に嘘やろ。
A-ko, who is knowledgeable about the industry (pseudonym). What? There's no way she's knowledgeable. It must be a lie.
あ、モザイクをかけてあげるのね。
Ah, we have to apply pixelation to her face.
はいはいはいはい、なるほどのじゃ。なるほど、なるほど。
Yes, yes, yes, yes, I see. I see, I see.
分かってきたのじゃ。
I've got the hang of this.
あからさまに
Clearly...
のじゃ。熱いのじゃ。
It's hot.
ひひひひ。すごいうつ伏せしてる。
He's totally face-down.
く、首折れる。
H-His neck is going to break.
この角度で、この角度で、湯に落ちたら、熱くなくても、
Falling into the tub at this angle... even if it's not hot,
熱くなくても危ないのじゃ。
even if it's not hot, it's dangerous.
しかもさ、若い、
And besides...
若い子供とかちゃんやったらさ、身体柔らかいから大丈夫かもじゃけどさ、
If it's a young child, their body is flexible, so they might be fine, but...
あの、大人がこれやるとガチで骨折するのじゃ。
if an adult does this, they'll seriously break a bone.
骨折しちゃうのじゃ。
They'll break a bone.
よし、次行きますのじゃ。のじゃ。
Alright, let's move on to the next one.
のじゃ。
Yeah.
第81問
Question 81
アイドルB子ちゃんが始球式を行います。のじゃ。
Idol B-ko will hold the ceremonial first pitch.
あ、頑張って打つよ。
Ah, I'll do my best to hit it.
来た、プレイスキル、プレイスキル来た。よし、よし。
Here it comes, play skill, my play skill is coming. Okay, okay.
はっ！来たーーー！
Ha! Here it comes!
当たったのじゃ。
It hit!
暗殺教室でこれ覚えたのじゃ。
I learned this from Assassination Classroom.
何？あ、あ、あ、あのじゃ、のじゃ、ん？
What? Ah, ah, ah... hmm?
第82問
Question 82
何？これ何？元ネタ知らないのじゃ。
What is this? What is this? I don't know the reference.
第83問
Question 83
え、撃っちゃダメ？何で？何で？何で？何で何で？
Eh, shouldn't I shoot? Why? Why? Why? Why, why?
ん？まもなく山頂。
Hmm? Almost at the summit.
ふん。何これ？
Hmm. What is this?
これは何がいけないの？何が起きているのじゃ？
What's wrong with this? What's happening?
え？これ何が起きているの？
Eh? What is happening here?
わし、山行かないから知らん。
I don't go to mountains, so I don't know.
第84問
Question 84
お、熊危ない。ちょちょちょ、死んだふり、死んだふり、死んだふり。
Oh, a bear is dangerous. Wait, wait, play dead, play dead, play dead.
でも、死んだふりしちゃダメなのじゃ。熊は、死んだふりしちゃダメ。あの背中を、
But you shouldn't play dead. With bears, you shouldn't play dead. You shouldn't turn your back...
背中を向けずに後ずさりなのじゃ。背中を向けずに後ずさり。
You must back away slowly without turning your back. Back away without turning your back.
死んだふりなんて、今の熊には通じないのじゃ。うん。
Playing dead won't work on bears nowadays. Yeah.
できるだけ自然界にない音を出しながら、背中を向けて、後ずさり。
While making noises that don't exist in nature as much as possible, back away without turning your back.
第85問
Question 85
でもどうしてもヤバい時は、あの、首を、首を守って、あの、小さくなるのじゃ。前かがみ。
But when you really have no choice, protect your neck and curl up. Bend forward.
首を守って小さくなって、あの、
Protect your neck, curl up, and...
何？ダンゴムシの、ダンゴムシのポーズをとるのじゃ。あの首、首、急所を下げるのじゃ。
take the pill bug pose. Lower your neck, protect your vital spot.
熊はガチ怖なのじゃ。
Bears are seriously terrifying.
うん。
Yeah.
天敵なのじゃ。山で暮らしている時の天敵、熊。普通にめちゃくちゃ怖かったのじゃ。
It's my natural enemy. The natural enemy when living in the mountains, a bear. It was honestly super scary.
危なかったのじゃ。
It was dangerous.
うん。怖いのじゃ。
Yeah, it's scary.
お水飲むのじゃ。
I'm going to drink some water.
よいしょ。よいしょ。
There we go. There we go.
父が買ってきてくれたのじゃ。
My father bought this for me.
のど飴舐めたのじゃ。
I'm having a cough drop.
行くのじゃ。ん。
Let's go. Mmh.
第86問
[Question 86]
え、シートベルト良くないのじゃ。シートベルトするのじゃ。ちょい、ちょい、ちょい。危ないのじゃ。
Eh? The seatbelt is bad. Put on your seatbelt. Hold on, hold on. It's dangerous.
絶対に、後部座席であろうとも、どんな時であろうともシートベルトはするのじゃ。
Absolutely, even in the back seat, no matter when, you must wear a seatbelt.
危ないのじゃ。死んじゃう。ライフ一つしかない、人間。サラマンダーにも一つしかない。
It's dangerous. You'll die. Humans only have one life. Salamanders only have one too.
この問題わかる人。なに？
"Who knows the answer to this question?" What?
あ、よし。あのね、この保護者参観の時にね、あの、自信なさげに親にアピールするためにあげる子供、愛おしいのじゃ。
Ah, nice. You know, during parents' day, that kid raising their hand nervously just to show off to their parent is so precious.
愛おしいのじゃ。よし。
It's precious. Alright.
いいこと。左見てる。あ、右を見る。左を見る。
Good. Looking left. Ah, looking right. Looking left.
右を見る。左を見る。
Looking right. Looking left.
みんな早いのじゃ。みんな早いのじゃ。
Everyone is so fast. Everyone is so fast.
あ！UFO！UFO！UFO！UFO！UFO！UFO！UFOいるのじゃ！
Ah! UFO! UFO! UFO! UFO! UFO! UFO! There's a UFO!
なに？何？何？今、何が起きたのじゃ？
What? What? What? What just happened?
のじゃ。UFOすごいのじゃ。ソピア、捕まえるのじゃ。
Wow, that UFO is amazing. Sophia, catch it.
お前。何？ん？
"You." What? Hm?
あ、出た、なろう系あるある。なろう系あるある。
Ah, here it is, the typical Isekai trope. The typical Isekai trope.
カップルを助けて、カップルを助けて、あの、転スラを導入。転スラの導入、これなのじゃ。
Saving a couple, saving a couple, and then starting a "Slime Isekai". This is how "Slime" started.
うん。
Yeah.
宇宙人、質問にYESなら手を上げろ。
Alien: "If yes to the question, raise your hand."
NOなら手を下げろ。了解のじゃ。
"If no, lower your hand." Got it.
行くのじゃ。
Here we go.
地球を滅ぼされたくなければ空気を読め。了解。
"If you don't want Earth to be destroyed, read the room." Got it.
お前は地球人か？まあ、そうなのじゃ。
"Are you an Earthling?" Well, yes.
地球を滅ぼされたくない。
"You don't want Earth to be destroyed."
地球を滅ぼされ…あ、あ、いや、これやめて。なく…あ。
"You don't want Earth..." Ah, wait, stop this! "Not..." Ah.
ん？一昨日の明日、明後日、一昨日…あ、あ。
Huh? "The day before yesterday's tomorrow..." Ah, ah.
痩せて、いな、いない。痩せていない。痩せていない。痩せていない。ちょ、ちょ。
"Are you thin?" No, I'm not. I'm not thin. I'm not thin. I'm not thin. Wait, wait.
何かが、見て、ちょ。一回上げたら下げれないのじゃ。ねえ、一回上げたら下げれない。
"What did you see..." Wait. Once I raise it, I can't lower it. Hey, once raised, I can't lower it.
秘密は守れる？守れる、守れるのじゃ。ねえ、ねえ、のじゃ！
"Can you keep a secret?" I can! I can! Hey, hey, seriously!
か、か、かゆいところ。あ、かゆいところ。あるって言っても止めてくれないのじゃ。
"Do you have... an itchy spot?" Even if I say I do, they won't stop.
お前に地球を守るヒーローをやってもらう。え、かっこいいやつ。やっぱ、なろう系なのじゃ。
"We will have you be a hero who protects Earth." Eh, that's cool! It really is an Isekai.
ねえ、どうやって下げたらいいの？なんか、
Hey, how do I lower my hand? Somehow...
な、何もできずに終わったのじゃ。人生のよう。
It ended without me being able to do anything. Just like life.
人生は何かを成し遂げて欲しい。そう。
I want to achieve something in life. Yes.
何もできずに終わった。わし、わしのなろう系が。わしのなろう系失敗。
It ended with me doing nothing. My... my Isekai story... My Isekai story failed!
わしの、わしのなろう系失敗なのじゃ。のじゃ。
My... my Isekai story failed. Oh no...
えー、かっこよく助けたかったのじゃ。スキル、スキル、てんこ盛りの欲しかったのじゃ。
Aww, I wanted to save them in a cool way. I wanted to have tons of skills.
91問目。キャー助けて。
Question 91. "Kyaa! Help me!"
ん？お！変身してる。すごい。
Huh? Oh! He's transforming. Awesome.
変身してる。これは、し、し、指示。これは指示。ツイッターに書き込んじゃダメ。今の、今の子すぐツイッターに書き込むから。ダメなのじゃ。
He transformed. This is... an instruction! This is an instruction! Don't tweet about this. Kids nowadays tweet everything immediately. Don't do it.
なんでやねん。アホちゃうか。
"Why though?" "Are you stupid?"
エスカレーターはダメじゃよ。危ないから。絶対どかないのじゃ。絶対に。
You shouldn't do that on an escalator. It's dangerous. They won't budge. Absolutely not.
だって、歩く方が悪いのじゃ。
Because the ones walking are in the wrong.
第93問
[Question 93]
議題、あのバンドの今後の活動方針。解散、ボーカルソロデビュー。
"Agenda: The future direction of that band. Dissolution, vocalist solo debut."
ああ、下をね。下に下がる系ね。ふんふんふん。
Ah, the bottom one. The "going down" one, right? I see, I see.
第94問
[Question 94]
あ、出た。さっき滑ってたバンド。エンジェル力見せて欲しいのじゃ。
Ah, there they are. The band that was failing earlier. I want to see their angel power.
行くのじゃ。
Here we go.
ベースってこの世の楽器で一番かっこよくて…え、
"The bass is the coolest instrument in the world..." Eh?
え？そういうのは令和にふさわしくないのじゃ。
Eh? That kind of thing isn't appropriate for the Reiwa era.
え？そういうのも令和にふさわしくないのじゃ。
Eh? That isn't appropriate for the Reiwa era either.
不安を煽ることはやめて欲しいのじゃ。これはいいと思っているなら、
I wish they would stop stirring up anxiety. If they think this is okay...
あの、世間に鈍感すぎるのじゃ。今の時代を見て売り出さないと、誰にも見てもらえませんのじゃ。のじゃ。
They're way too out of touch with the world. If you don't market yourself based on the current times, nobody will watch you.
節電中。ん？
"Saving electricity." Hm?
あ、髪の毛が。ちょ、もうちょ、もうちょい優しく。のじゃ。
Ah, the hair. Wait, a bit... a bit gentler. Oh dear.
ふんふんふん
Hmm hmm hmm.
そこはかとなく
Somehow...
最後何が起きた？最後何が起きたのじゃ？
What happened at the end? What happened at the end?
のじゃ？
Did it?
いけた？
Did we make it?
第96問
Question 96!
今日は絶対に座るぞ。何？
"Today, I will definitely sit down." What?
はい。最初から、最初からこういうとこ座っておくのじゃ。
Yes. We should sit in a place like this from the very beginning.
あっ
Ah.
のじゃ？
Really?
ヒマだな…久しぶりに惑星でも…
"I'm bored... Maybe I'll attack a planet..."
いや、やっぱヒーローバトル見たいから。バトル見たい！戦いたいじゃろ？何もないものを殲滅したとて、それが本当に快楽になるか？いや、ならない！
No, actually, I want to see a hero battle. I want to see a battle! You want to fight, right? Even if you annihilate something that has nothing, will that really bring pleasure? No, it won't!
強き者と戦うこと、そして戦って勝つことこそが、
Fighting against the strong, and fighting and winning is precisely what...
のじゃああ！あ！
Oh my goodness! Ah!
え？強すぎたのじゃ。
Eh? It was too strong.
人間弱い。
Humans are weak.
人間弱いのじゃ。第99問
Humans are weak. Question 99.
え、感動的なシーン？
Eh, a touching scene?
久しぶり。
"It's been a while."
来てくれたんだ…
"You came..."
ずっと会いたかったんだよ。
"I've always wanted to see you."
もっと強く手を握ってて。
"Hold my hand tighter."
なつかしいなあ、この感じ。
"How nostalgic, this feeling."
何？エモパート来たのじゃ？
What? Is this the emotional part?
心霊写真を写メでくれたよね。
"You sent me a ghost photo on my phone, right?"
アレ、携帯の待受けにしてるんだよ…あははは！
"I use that as my phone wallpaper, you know..." Ahaha!
いや、違う、笑い事じゃないか。
No, wait, it's not a laughing matter.
こういう最後の時ならどういう些細なことでも、それがその子の思い出になる。
At a final moment like this, even the most trivial things, that becomes their memory.
そうかも。それを笑うのは失礼なのじゃ。
That might be so. It's rude of me to laugh at it.
全部知ってるんだからね。
"I know everything, you know."
もっと一緒に居ればよかったな。病気なのかな？
"I wish we had spent more time together." Is she sick?
怪獣ってホントにいるんだね。ふん。
"So monsters really do exist." Hmm.
私つぶされちゃったヨ。つぶされちゃった？
"I got crushed." "I got crushed"?
私と初めて会った日、覚えてる？
"Do you remember the day we first met?"
あなた、優柔不断だから、
"Because you are indecisive,"
私のことは忘れて、
"forget about me,"
早く新しい人を見つけてね。恋人じゃ！
"and find someone new soon." She was a lover!
なんか涙が止まんない。さっきの倒された人？
"Somehow, I can't stop crying." Is this the person who got defeated earlier?
そんな！ヒーローが負けたから？わしが世界変えちゃった？空気読めなくてごめんね。
No way! Is it because the hero lost? Did I change the world? "Sorry for not reading the room."
わ、わしのせいで結末が…そんな…
B-Because of me, the ending is... No way...
そんな…いつも周りの人に気配りできる
No way... "you always consider those around you"
優しいあなた大好きだったよ。え？そんな…わしのせい？
"I loved your kind self." Eh? No way... is it because of me?
でも空気なんて読まなくていい時も
"But even at times when you don't need to read the room"
あることを忘れないでね。
"don't forget that there are such moments."
ありがとう。え、わしのせいで？
"Thank you." Eh, because of me?
さようなら…一人の人…空気読まないと…
"Goodbye..." A single person... if I don't read the room...
死にたくないよ。人を殺しかねない？
"I don't want to die." Could I have killed someone?
そんな…そんな悲しいのじゃ。うう、悲しいのじゃ。え？
No way... that is so sad. Oh, it's so sad. Eh?
バタフライエフェクトってやつ？直接的にわしが殺しちゃった？
Is this what they call the butterfly effect? Did I directly kill them?
第100問。何？何何何？
Question 100. What? What, what, what?
あ、最後のね。
Ah, the last one.
最後のね。
The last one.
のじゃーー！
No way!
なんとなしに読めてるっぽい。
Somehow reading it.
ええ？最後、最後わしバッドエンドにしちゃったの？バッドエンドにしちゃったのじゃ？
Eh? Did I make it a bad ending at the very end? Did I make it a bad ending?
悲しいのじゃ。悲しいのじゃ。
It's so sad. It's so sad.
総合結果見るのじゃ。ふん。
Let's look at the overall results. Hmm.
え、なんかあんまり高くない。そうなの？
Eh, it's not that high. Really?
え？なんか、なんか、なんか
Eh? Somehow, somehow, somehow...
なんか微妙な、なんか微妙な読めなさ、それが一番傷つくのじゃ。
A somewhat subtle inability to read the room, that hurts the most.
微妙、微妙な、微妙な、微妙な読めなさなのじゃ。ええー。
A subtle, subtle, subtle, subtle inability to read. Ehhh.
わし人間、人間まだだめ？わしカメレオンなのじゃ？
Am I not ready to be a human yet? Am I a chameleon?
サラマンダーなのに、サラマンダーなのに、カメレオン？
Even though I'm a salamander, even though I'm a salamander, a chameleon?
これから自認カメレオンで生きていくのじゃ。
From now on, I will live identifying as a chameleon.
わしはカメレオンですのじゃ。
I am a chameleon.
おしまいなのじゃーー！
It's the end!
難しいのじゃーー！
It was so hard!
人間に溶け込むのめちゃくちゃ難しかったのじゃ。カメレオン火吹けないよ、でも。火吹けないのじゃ。
Blending in with humans was incredibly difficult. But chameleons can't breathe fire. I can't breathe fire.
元の部屋に、も…
Back to the original room...
取るか。
Should I choose...
元の部屋に戻りますのじゃ。
Let's return to the original room!
よいしょ！
Heave-ho!
ふん！
Hmph!
のじゃーーー！
Noja---!
うーん、なんか難しかったのじゃ。
Hmm, that was kind of difficult, noja.
なんか難しかったのじゃ。
It was kind of difficult, noja.
もっと空気を読むって簡単なのかなと思ってたけど、
I thought reading the room would be easier, but...
人間って考えること多いの？
do humans have a lot to think about?
てか、わし思ったんじゃが、空気を読むの何がむずいかって話をしてい？
Anyway, I was thinking, can I talk about what's so difficult about reading the room?
空気を読むためには、まずその、その場における正解を、その共通認識、その場にある共通認識をなんか正しく認識しておかなきゃいかんじゃろ？
To read the room, first, you have to correctly recognize the correct answer in that situation, that common understanding, the common understanding in that place, right?
それって知識ゲーじゃない？
Isn't that a knowledge game?
それって経験とかさ、経験に基づいたさ、知識ゲーでさ。
Isn't that like experience, based on experience, a knowledge game?
なんか人間界のさ、空気読むってさ、誰も教えてくんないのじゃ。
Like, in the human world, no one teaches you how to read the room, noja.
ちっちゃい頃とかだとさ、なんかその、空気読めないとさ、省かれるとかさ、そういう目に見えてね、
When you're small, if you can't read the room, you get excluded, visibly,
空気が読めないからこそ、なんか悪いこととかがわかりやすく起きるけど、
because you can't read the room, bad things happen in an obvious way, but...
大人になったらもういちいち誰も指摘してくれなくなるから、
when you become an adult, no one points it out to you anymore, so...
なんか空気を読むってめちゃくちゃ高等スキルなんじゃないの？
reading the room is like an incredibly high-level skill, isn't it?
めちゃむずくない？
Isn't it super hard?
相手の心を感じる、思いやりとかってさ、できるだけさ、
Feeling the other person's heart, like consideration, as much as possible...
やってるつもりなんだけど、やってるつもりなんだけどさ、
I intend to do it, I really intend to, but...
なんかその、知識がさ、ある程度ないとさ、むずくない？
without a certain amount of knowledge, isn't it hard?
人間のことあんまり傷つけたくないのじゃ。
I don't want to hurt humans too much, noja.
傷つけたくないから、できるだけ空気って読みたいけど、
Because I don't want to hurt them, I want to read the room as much as possible, but...
習得するのがすごい難しいのじゃ。
learning it is extremely difficult, noja.
ね。
Right?
で、その経験もさ、経験を積める環境と積めない環境があるじゃん。
And about that experience, there are environments where you can gain experience and ones where you can't, right?
どうしたらいいのじゃ？
What should I do, noja?
どこにいたら適切な経験が積めるのじゃ？
Where should I be to gain appropriate experience, noja?
ある程度集団の中に属さないと、そういう空気を読むための
I feel like without belonging to a group to some extent,
訓練ってできない気がするのじゃ。
you can't train yourself to read the room like that, noja.
でもわしコミュニケーションのこと暗記ゲーだと思っているよ、正直。
But honestly, I think communication is a memorization game.
なんか、あ、これしたら人間喜ぶんだとか、
Like, "Oh, doing this makes humans happy," or...
これしたら人間悲しむのかとか、
"doing this makes them sad," or...
あ、こういうことを言うと人間は嫌な気持ちになるらしいとか、
"saying this seems to make humans feel bad,"
なんかそういうのをね、覚えて、覚えるたびに修正はしてるんじゃが、
I learn things like that, and every time I learn, I adjust, but...
なかなか、なかなか難しいのじゃ。
it's quite, quite difficult, noja.
しきしき。野球の始球式。野球の始球式って何なのじゃ？
Shiki-shiki. Baseball's ceremonial first pitch. What is a ceremonial first pitch?
なんか女性声優さんとかが、おっ！先輩もやってた。先輩もやってたやつ？
Like female voice actresses do—Oh! A senior did it too. A senior did that too?
なんか、そういう、なんじゃろな。特定の分野、例えばアニメとかさ。
Like, those, what is it. A specific field, like anime.
このアニメを知らないと読めない空気とかさ。
A vibe you can't read unless you know this anime.
そのガンダム知らないとどっち選べばいいかわかんないとこあったじゃろ？
There was a part where you wouldn't know which to choose unless you knew Gundam, right?
そういうさ、なんかその、特定のコンテンツに触れてないと
Those kinds of things, if you haven't been exposed to specific content,
読めない空気ってのが結構あると思うんじゃよ。
I think there are quite a lot of vibes you can't read.
それって難しくない？
Isn't that difficult?
だから多分人間たちは、人気コンテンツを見たり、履修したりするんじゃろうな。
So that's probably why humans watch or study popular content.
なんか、何だろう、流行ってるドラマを見るとか流行ってる映画を見るって、
Like, what is it, watching a trendy drama or watching a trendy movie,
その、トークテーマ、トークテーマとしてその、時事ネタみたいなの、
as a talk theme, as a talk theme, like current events...
乗っ、乗っとくかみたいなのもあるかもじゃけど、
like jumping on the bandwagon, there might be that too, but...
なんかそれ以上にふとした時に、空気を読むために、習得してる？
more than that, at unexpected moments, to read the room, are they acquiring it?
人間が、社会で、社会的に生きてくために、
Aren't humans, in society, in order to live socially,
頑張ってるんじゃない？
working hard?
だから倍速で見る若者がいる。なるほどね！
That's why there are young people who watch on double speed. I see!
じゃあ別にそのコンテンツ自身に興味があるというよりかは、コンテンツじゃなくて、
So it's not really that they are interested in the content itself, but rather than the content,
群れから省かれないように、群れから省かれないために、
so they don't get excluded from the pack, in order not to be excluded from the pack,
知識としてつけておくみたいな。へぇー！色んな
they acquire it as knowledge. Wow! There are various...
それも果たして楽しみ方なのかと言われると微妙なんじゃが、
Whether that can really be called a way of enjoying it is questionable, but
そういうのもあるんじゃな。
there are those kinds of reasons too, I guess.
群れで生きていくということ。
What it means to live in a pack.
んー、なるほどな、のじゃ。人間社会。
Hmm, I see, noja. Human society.
でも、でも、群れに属するメリットって結構いっぱいあるから、
But, but, there are actually a lot of merits to belonging to a pack, so...
あるし、
and...
やっぱ一人ぼっちは寂しいから
Being all alone is lonely after all,
一人ぼっちは寂しいから
since being all alone is lonely.
そういうことをしたくなる人間の気持ちもわかるのじゃ。うん。
I can understand why humans would want to do that. Yes.
だからなんか、例えば今職場でアチメラが大流行りしていたとして
So, for example, let's say Achimera is a huge trend at your workplace right now.
今ね、もしね、お主の職場でアチメラが大流行りしていたとして
If Achimera is indeed a huge trend at your workplace,
職場の人に勧められたから、その、トークデッキ、
and someone there recommended it, so...
トークデッキのためにアチメラの配信見てみるかって人がこの中にいるかもしれないけど
there might be some of you here watching to build your "talk deck."
わし的にはそれも十分社会的な行動だと思うのじゃ、うん。
But to me, that's still a perfectly social activity. Yes.
その義務感で見ている人間がいたとして
Even if there are people watching out of a sense of obligation,
そういう人間にも好きになってもらえるように頑張ろうって思うのじゃ。うん。
it makes me want to work hard so they'll grow to like me too. Yes.
なんか、「興味ないけど義務感で見たけど意外とおもろいやん」とか
Like, "I wasn't interested and only watched out of obligation, but this is actually pretty fun,"
「意外と好きやん」って思ってもらえるように、
or "I actually quite like this." To make them feel that way,
頑張ろうと思いますのじゃ。
I want to do my very best.
でも、やっぱ「好きだから」って理由で見るのが
But watching simply because you "like it"
やっぱり一番いい感情、いいことだと思う。健康にも、精神的にもね。
is definitely the best feeling. For both physical and mental health.
いいと思うから、楽しんで見てもらえると嬉しいの。
So I'd be happy if you can just enjoy watching.
うん。だから
Yes. So,
ずっと好きでいてもらえるように頑張ろうと思うのじゃ。うん。
I'll do my best so you will keep liking me. Yes.
そう思うのじゃ。うん。
That's what I think. Yes.
頑張るのじゃ。うん！
I'll do my best. Yes!
今日はこの辺でおしまいにしようと…あ！
I should wrap up today's stream around here... Ah!
えーっと、ちょっと待っての。
Um, hold on a second.
ほっ！
Ho!
明日の配信告知をするのじゃー！
I'm going to make an announcement for tomorrow's stream!
I'm going to announce tomorrow's stream!
明日の19時からはこちら！
Tomorrow at 7:00 PM is this!
アチメラのインターネット防災訓練！
Achimera's Internet Disaster Prevention Training!
インターネット防災訓練をしますのじゃ。初配信でちょこっと行ったこと、
We will do internet disaster prevention training. It's about what we briefly covered in my debut stream,
インターネットを使うにおいて、気をつけたほうがいいこと、
the things to be careful about when using the internet.
サラマンダーが体当たりで得た知識を、わしが体当たりで得た知識を
The knowledge this Salamander gained firsthand—knowledge I acquired by running headfirst—
お主らに教授していこうと、
I'll be passing on to all of you.
教えてあげようと思いますのじゃー！
I'll teach you all about it!
インターネットリテラシーのお勉強なのじゃー！
It's time to study internet literacy!
わしと共に防災訓練をしましょう。19時から！
Let's do disaster prevention training together. From 7:00 PM!
明日の19時から行いますのじゃ。おむ。
We'll be doing it tomorrow starting from 7:00 PM. Yes.
まだスライドの準備してないから、今日配信終わったらすっごい頑張って準備しようと思いますのじゃ。
I haven't prepared the slides yet, so once today's stream ends, I'll work really hard to prepare them.
いい配信にできるように頑張るのじゃ。明日も遊びに来てほしいのじゃー！
I'll do my best to make it a great stream. I hope you'll come hang out tomorrow too!
あ、あとね、何だっけ？あれやってみたい、レイドってやつやってみたい。
Oh, and also, what was it? I want to try that... I want to try doing a Raid.
ちょっとやり方を、探していいかの？
Can I look up how to do it real quick?
ん？どこからやるのじゃ？
Hmm? Where do I do it from?
レイドってどうやってやるのかな？
How do you do a Raid, I wonder?
ちょっと調べていい？ちょっとお主らも待っててくれる？
Can I look it up? Could you all wait for a bit?
やり方がわからないのじゃ。
I don't know how to do it.
やり方がわからないのじゃ。前できたのに！
I don't know how to do it, even though I did it before!
前できたのに、あ、これ！
Even though I did it before... Ah, this!
のじゃ。
I see.
こう、
Like this...
こうなんじゃない？できたー！
Isn't it like this? I did it!
よいしょ。
There we go.
やり方わかった！
I figured it out!
ソフィアの周りにお主らを飛ばすのじゃ。
I'm going to send you all over to Sophia's stream.
なんか昨日、アソビマワリタイのメンバーがやってて「いいな」って思って、わしもやってみたいって思ったからやってみようと思うのじゃ。
Yesterday, the Asobimawaritai members were doing it, and I thought it was neat, so I wanted to try it out too.
うん。
Yeah.
やってみますのじゃ！
I'm going to try it!
じゃあ、今日の配信は、これで、おしまいですのじゃー！
Well then, today's stream is wrapping up here!
また、次の配信で会いたいのじゃ。
I hope to see you in the next stream.
終わりの挨拶は、えっと、さらばじゃで、
The ending greeting will be, let's see, "Saraba-ja"...
さらばじゃでおしまいにしますのじゃ。
We'll end things with "Saraba-ja".
行くのじゃー！
Here we go!
それではお主ら、さらばじゃーー！！
And so, everyone, saraba-ja!!
のじゃ。
Bye-bye.